Coming up next,
we have Jolene L Armstrong
and looks like we have Monique
Tschofen as well.
So I'll just turn it over to them
and allow them to introduce themselves
and get us started.
Hi. I am always confused.
Which which thing is showing is that.
Are you seeing a little row on the bottom
or just the slide?
Yeah. No, that slide.
Just slide.
Okay. Fabulous.
Okay.
Well hello everybody.
Great panel to be wrapping up today.
And thanks to our organizers
and panel chair.
So I'm Monique Tschofen from Toronto
Metropolitan University
and I'm Jolene
Armstrong from Athabasca University.
Both of us are in Canada.
We are two among the members of the Nine
Women Decameron Collective.
Caitlin Fisher
who's here is one lychee fan and offline
as well, with whom we've worked on
a large body of research creation projects
that each tried to take on a shared
crisis, starting with the pandemic.
And we used storytelling
and a practice of radical collective care
to create large anthology
style works and check out our our work
at the next exhibition,
which has just been launched.
Yeah.
So our more recent work together
as a duo has related
to our sense of the urgency
of the poly crisis of the Anthropocene.
So in Fire and Water, which we exhibited
last year at Ello in Toronto,
we created an installation work
that featured my sculpture of water,
where sheets of water
poured over an encyclopedia
open to the page on erosion
to talk about flooding, and
this was accompanied by Monique's
projector art film, a Markov
generated poem using the New York
Times coverage of the Palisades
wildfires in California,
which raised the critical problem
of AI water usage
in California and globally.
Our other project,
or our next project after that? In
our interactive documentary,
we designed an interactive, living,
creative and data driven assemblage
that used a wide range of analog
and digital documentary practices
which included water coloring, film
photography, mapping and writing.
Anchored in theories of embodiment
that tackled the eco theory
notion of solar, that is, the distress
caused by environmental change,
and it was a term that has been coined
by a couple of different
independent researchers.
But we discovered it
through Albrecht at all, and
we were exploring the research questions
around our experimentations
that both crystallized
and obscured these processes.
And then Monique's film
documentary, Aquifer
Before the Waters Rise,
in, which talks about water.
But we're here to talk
about our latest work
in progress,
which is a sound project that continues
along these lines of thinking
and is is still growing.
So previous papers in this panel
have talked about handing agency
off to a machine.
Our work starts from a paradoxical desire
to use digital tools
to criticize the technocratic imaginary,
and to reconsider agency,
to include the more than human world.
But we understand that to mean the
the natural world.
So Water Songs is a work
that deliberately sits between a number of
including digital humanities
and documentary,
but also ecological sound art.
And we're trying to circumvent
our seduction by the image
and our seduction by machines,
and instead provoke forms of deep
listening practices of attention
that we think are crucial
for our relationship with the environment.
So our
inspiration for this came
after watching the deeply moving
and profoundly thought provoking
documentary film Geographies of Silence.
So if you haven't seen this, we are due to
to take some time to watch it.
It's free and accessible on the,
I believe, on the National Film
Board of Canada as website or CBC one
or the other account member,
we started thinking more about sound
as the filmmaker documentarian
documentarian Jacqueline
Mills used a contact mic
to record the inaudible to the human ear
sounds that came from old wood, seaweed
and other objects that had been standing
on Sable Island for decades.
The cryptic sounding
clicks and hums from these objects
felt really important to hear.
I felt a vulnerability
not unlike when music moves you to tears.
The sounds trigger emotional responses
that are often
not as privileged
as our visual culture production.
So it was really important moment
for both of us
and what we thought was so revealing
to approach the
this documentary and our own documentation
of our environment
in a way that moves beyond the ordinary
capturing of our perception.
So I wondered what other sounds are
out there that we could capture
and hate the word capture,
that we could record or perhaps tap into
from the non-living natural environment
or the living natural environment.
So what can we learn?
We learn to perceive by listening in a way
that we are usually unable to do.
So we track down the set of contact,
acoustic and aquatic mix that Mills use
from a creator and sound artist
by the name of Jazz
Riley French, who's based in the UK
and who has built an impressive
of natural micro and recordings.
And he built a sea
to set of those microphones.
One of the
things that I adored about Mills
film of Seattle Islands is that, well,
this is a place
that has a charismatic herd of wild horses
scampering around beautiful sand dunes.
The filmmaker, as to the sublime
esthetics, and instead zoomed in
on a tiny insect
moving across a grain of sand.
Its attention
to what human culture has told us
not to notice
that those are the most moving
now in our work, with the collective
and with each other.
Jolene.
And my approach has often
taken the form of experiments.
We're very motivated by questions
that start what would happen if,
well, a great deal of eco sound
art attends to the noises that animals
or like whale song or birdsong
or plants make, like wind and trees.
We began to use our mics to listen
elementary, putting probes
in and on tree trunks, bark,
moss, water, dirt, sand, and even stone.
Like mills.
We have asked
what can listening in on our environment
and finding ways to tap into sounds
that are just beyond human perception.
Tell us about the natural world around us,
and the climate and environmental
changes that have already impacted
our immediate environments.
So as we took our microphones
and recorders
and take them to tree tongues, mushrooms,
logs and drop them into rivers, ponds,
beaches, snow banks and puddles rerecorded
the ambient sounds around us.
But more specifically,
we were trying to capture the sounds that
we didn't even realize, or there
and are imperceptible to human ears.
Without this sort of intentional
recording and amplification.
We built the Water Song site in scaler
in a Canadian installation
that hopefully is immune to the problems
of the country south of us,
which we won't get into
in this conversation.
Scalar has led us integrate maps and text
and keep
robust metadata for all of the media
that we have been incorporating.
So what is it not?
These
sounds are not organized as a library.
Although we love and
library of breaths,
they are not quite a soundscape
like Canadian composer or Murray Schafer
created with other artists,
but we wanted to avoid the urge
to bring the cognitive
tools of organizing and labeling.
And instead of reaching for
comprehensiveness, working through genera
and species like all of the snowbanks
or some of the puddles,
we allow their unevenness
and their strangeness to flourish.
What it is closest to you
is perhaps pulling Oliveros work,
and that we think about this
as a practice,
a technologically mediated prompting
of a mode of embodied attunement,
and one, moreover, that radically resists
our attraction to the modes we use
in our scholarly and creative lives,
like storing, interpreting, and declaring.
Above all, what we experience comes
closest to the Greek ideal of Thammasat.
In the idea of wonder,
which Plato and Aristotle established
was the grounds of philosophy
and later science itself.
This week my province was thick
with wildfire smoke from the north.
In Toronto, we breathed the worst
air on the planet for more than a day.
When Jolene and I went to the north
of Scotchman River in Edmonton in June
to record it,
the river was at its highest.
I happened to be on a boat in Alaska
when the hugest chunk of glacier
the captain had ever seen fell
into the sea.
The Anthropocene
operates at what Timothy Morton describes
as hyperscalers that are,
he says, viscous, which means they stick
to beings that are involved with them.
But he says they are non-local and involve
profoundly different temporalities
than the human scale ones.
We are used to what listening beyond
the human scale can do, we argue, is shift
these skills and radically reestablish
the particular, the local and the now.
And this is from Jez Riley French,
the maker of our microphones.
The most powerful outcome of listening
closely to environments as an art form
is how the process changes our perception
of them, and indeed our place in them.
Essential to this is the need
to allow locales to impose on us,
and not for us to impose
our expectations on them.
Yeah,
and just
adding to that, the sort of context
in which we find ourselves today, usually
where I'm from is blanketed in smoke.
But today, as of today,
we have received more
than our entire yearly average of rainfall
in less than 30 days.
And my house got flooded.
My mom's house got flooded,
everyone's houses flooded,
our underpasses, our
our city has been destroyed by flooding.
And so it feels very urgent
living in in the places
that we are living and paying attention
to the things that we're paying attention.
So as we were experimented,
we found that sound is a really potent
way to access these these poly crisis
that we seem to be dealing with
on a more and more urgent scale.
Water or its absence has become
a crucial index for where we are.
And so the unsupervised, I think
theme is that in our presentation
and in our work,
is that what we're trying to achieve
here is a response
to the fact that the unsupervised
pursuit of extractive
capitalism is directly hastening
the collapse of a livable environment.
And this is this is something that feels
extremely urgent in our
in our particular locations
and the events that have happened over
the last couple of weeks.
I just returned from Europe,
where I've never felt he and
and not just the heat,
but the crisis that that heat was causing
to infrastructure to people
and their daily lives and rhythms.
So many of the sound experiments start in
my backyard is very local,
and they document the effects of what,
until this year has been a decade long.
Drought and dryness, it turns out,
is audible in dirt and anthills and
and in trees that are reacting
and reorganizing their cellular structure
to respond to
these, these different situations.
And this year, this same yard
that I documented in this particular
slide is now basically a water feature.
Yeah.
So we see this work of deep listening
through the isolated
recordings of sounds,
of nature, of sub aural sounds and sounds
that exist on registers that humans can't
ordinarily perceive, but also reflect
and confront and effect ecological issues
as part of a broader ethical practice.
So by listening deeply to sounds
that might otherwise be dismissed
or as irrelevant or unremarked,
or as background noise for existence,
we can attune ourselves differently
and more ethically, responsibly,
responsibly to the natural environment
in which we coexist
with millions of other species.
And maybe you want to play
that little clip
there.
I hope I had the sound setting on.
Were you able to hear that?
No. Okay.
Yeah. Then I'd have to log into the Zim.
Forgive me. That's okay.
You know what? It's.
This is all in our exhibition piece that
that you can listen to at your leisure
if you so desired.
Yeah.
All right. So.
This experimental and non discursive
recording experiment
has demanded a skill
that we think is greatly needed
in the political environment
of the Anthropocene.
And that is listening.
Peterson and Brennan
were really helpful for us.
They underlined that listening
is a fundamentally
and necessarily relational experience
or scenting a person toward a frog,
a blender, rock traffic, radio, child,
or wind
opens to more than human relationships,
and they continue
listening is always listening with
with other people, with ghosts,
with animals, trees and plants,
and with acoustic spaces
and asking how people listen
as part of ethnographic research,
we necessarily listen with others
moving away from solitary
and agenda of human listening as sound
resonates across bodies and buildings.
This relational piece is has always been
really deeply embedded in our work
with a collective as well.
Yeah.
So yeah, one of the statements
that we've been thinking about
from Timothy Morton
a lot is the notion of melancholia.
So letting the dead stick in our throat,
this idea of a more ethically refined
and more than mourning way of existence.
So, yeah.
And the notion as well, necro politics,
the politics of death,
which is very much tied
to extractive capitalism
and all the
all the things that we're watching unfold
before us in the last couple of years
in particular, is up.
The Cameroonian philosopher
Achille and Bambi
came up with this term to describe the
death inflicting politics of colonialism
and the conditions where those in power
don't have to care who lives or dies.
So sounding the or the water songs.
Piece that we've been working on
and is on exhibition here
at l'Eau, is intended to be a life
affirming response to the ongoing threats
to humanity and our natural environments,
a response in which we have actively,
intentionally stretched ourselves
to think beyond human perception.
What can listening in in our environment
and finding ways to tap into these sights
and sounds and stories
tell us about the natural world around us
and really listening to things that we
don't understand, and that may not sound
significant, is is truly an exercise,
I think, in kind of humbling ourselves
as well, and decent language
dissenting the things that
we believe are the most important things.
And so what can we show
is that we can use various technologies
such as these, and contact
microphones and microscopes
to listen in on the stories
that tree trunks and moss
and bark and water tell us,
and that there is a pathway for humans
to learn from complex organisms
and the vibrations of non-living
natural matter by learning
how to listen differently.
And this is a sort of creative attempt,
I guess, to address the climate crisis
by conceiving of the world differently.
We can alter our human relationship
with the natural environment.
If we use our other senses
to perceive the living ness and aliveness
of everything around us, we can indeed
reverse the death drive of politics
by attuning ourselves more deeply,
more indebted, and more responsibly to
our natural environments.
Catherine
and her essay and object oriented feminism
tries to reclaim the term necrophilia
to describe a feminist philosophy
that takes dead objects as love objects.
And we find that these currents,
and especially feminist
ecology, feminist object oriented,
are the ones that most resonate with us
an act of love for what is dying,
where the transmigration of matter dry
and drought for flooded,
flooded for dry, a living for on fire
that is firmly mattered
and in placed anchors us.
It situates us in a moment
where we actually need to be acting.
What Stephanie Lovelace emphasizes,
moreover, is that these kinds of practices
bring us back into our bodies,
where we can see how we are embedded
and in context,
so that we have agency within.
So this method for navigating
sensory experience
is another takeaway that we would want.
Yeah.
So then taking a cue from this particular
theoretical stance, we approach
listening in on in the world around us,
not simply as listening to sound
that is a passing occurrence,
but rather as part of a larger narrative
and the larger narrative
being the story of our world.
So yeah.
So we're we're happy to,
I think, leave it at that.
And, and always happy to talk
more as well.
Thank you so much for listening to us.
Got it.
Listening, listening.